actually is the power of the people's
vote and I think the people should use
it to vote for so in this video I want
to pick up on a point that I made in a
previous video namely that our systems
are going to be incapable of solving
problems which they themselves have
created and so things like environmental
destruction and war and corruption and
inequality these things have always been
problems but technology has now reached
the point where we do these things so
well so efficiently that they've
actually become existential threats and
so the time has absolutely come to
re-examine the top-down rule driven
systems that we employ to organize
ourselves and so the top-down rule
driven procedural systems that we use
are complicated but the systems that
they seek to manage and control are
complex and so what I want to talk about
today rests on the incompatibility
between our systems which are
complicated and the natural systems the
people the societies the cultures the
natural environment with which they
interact and it is this fundamental
incompatible incompatibility which
creates these problems as forms of
pollution as externalities to the
imperfections of the system before I go
any further I would like to credit the
ideas in this are not at all mine Jordan
Hall and daniel trachtenberg I've been
listening to a lot of their stuff and
they talked a great deal about this and
so as Jordan would say insofar as you
find this interesting and enlightening
that's entirely down to them and to the
extent you which you to which you find
this confusing and pointless that's my
fault
and so I need to begin with an
explanation of the difference between
the complex and the complicated for
those of you not versed in this kind of
thing so both complex and complicated
systems can have lots and lots and lots
of independent parts the fundamental
difference between them is that in a
complicated system relationship of each
part of the system to the other parts
with with you interacts are very clearly
defined
whereas in a complex system the
relationship between each individual
part of the system is not at all clearly
defined because one thing influences
another influences another everything is
connected to everything else whereas in
a complicated system that is not the
case and so complicated things are
things like cars and aeroplanes and
timetables where you can follow through
from beginning to end and see very
clearly once that leads to no leads to
another leads to another leads to
another in a complex system you
absolutely cannot do that you feed
something in and essentially anything
can come out I mean is it not quite like
that they have tendencies and they have
ranges but basically a complex system
creates a great deal of randomness and
novelty and unpredictability whereas a
complicated system if you understand it
well is entirely predictable so that in
a nutshell is the difference between
complex and complicated and so it is my
contention in this video that top-down
rule driven procedural algorithmic
systems are incapable of effectively
interfacing with natural systems which
are complex and I mean this occurs at
every level every organism is complex
within its own right each ecosystem is
complex ecosystems linked together in
complex ways the complexity is across
all scales and so I'd like to try and
illustrate the process if you will by
use of an example and the example I
picked is the tax code now the tax code
is a very important thing right if you
the purpose of the tax code is a
solution to the problem of how can very
large numbers of people who don't know
each other
collaborate on things which are going to
be good for everyone and collaboratively
provide the resources to undertake these
projects and so that's essentially what
the tax system is seeking to do to
equitably get everybody can to
contribute a fair amount for their
circumstances so that there is enough
from the society as a whole to do that
which will benefit the society as a
whole that's that's the idea of the tax
code that's the spirit of it tax code
would have started out reasonably
straightforward right
but then as societies become more varied
and more diverse in their activities and
there are more members of the society
there are more situations and so the
rules of the tax code need to get more
complicated to take into account all of
the new circumstances which you've
cropped up but of course complex systems
have a virtually limitless capacity to
throw up novel situations and so you're
always going to get situations where
somebody doesn't fit into one category
or another that is that this system is
created and so you start getting
arguments and this is one of the forms
of pollution that I'm talking about you
now have disputes you have resentment
you have bad feeling between the payer
of the tax and the collector of the tax
and if you remember that the spirit of
the tax code is to collectively do
things that things which are benefit to
all of us that should not be the case
right paying taxes noam chomsky makes
this point that the annual day of paying
taxes should be a day of celebration
when we get to implement the programs
which we have collectively agreed upon
but of course that is not the case right
and that's kind of exactly what I'm
talking about so anyway following on
from where I was the complex systems
ability to create novel situations puts
a demand on the complicated system to
create ever more and more rules and sub
rules and caveats and exceptions and so
on and this makes the tax code so
complicated that nobody can navigate it
anymore it becomes too cumbersome for
anybody to really understand which means
it can now be exploited clever
accountants clever lawyers can find
loopholes in the tax code so that people
can start to legally avoid paying their
taxes and these kinds of tactics are
only available to the rich and powerful
and so you now start getting inequity
built into the system because the rich
people who can afford the clever
accountants are not paying anywhere near
as much tax as they should do whereas
the poor schlubs
who are working every day get tax taken
before they even get it in their hands
you know they don't have to pay it over
they get it they deducted at source and
so this is another form of pollution
inequality is exacerbated by this tax so
code because the rich are paying as much
as they should in the poor repay that an
unreasonable burden now goes on to poor
people so that's the basic idea but then
of course there's more to it than that
right as tax revenues increase
because the society gets more prosperous
there are more members of the society so
tax revenues increased government has
more money to spend government gets
larger they have more they find more
things to spend money on military
spending goes up major infrastructure
projects go up and vanity projects go up
and so the demand of the states attacks
its citizens goes up as well and so the
spirit of the thing at some point gets
lost instead of it being a collaborative
thing for the benefit of all it's now
the government against its citizens
trying to extract as much as it can from
them and then of course you get to the
stage where right now where rich people
Lobby the government in order to make
changes to the cat tax code so that they
can benefit from it and so this is this
is the sort of final demise if you like
it makes a nonsense of the whole thing
where those that make the rules can
simply change the rules to their
advantage as everybody else's expense it
it creates resentment it creates
increasing inequality and it creates and
this is the overall point creates too
much tension between the complex and the
complicated and when the tension between
these two things gets too great it's not
the complex which is going to break down
is been around for billions of years and
that's not the complex than break down
as the complicated which is going to
break down and this idea of unbearable
tension between the complex and the
complicated can be seen all over the
place when we've got crises wherever we
look we have a cultural crisis as
evidenced by the dramatic increases in
depression and suicide and drug
addiction rates we have a political
crisis as evidenced by the fact that
there are far-right parties gaining
strength everywhere we've got
authoritarianism both sides of the
Atlantic now we all know we're enduring
an environmental crisis where we're
wiping out habitats and species at an
unbelievable rate polluting air sea
river and land as fast as we possibly
can and all of these things are
basically exactly the story that I've
already described you the tension
between the complicated systems we use
to harness and interact with the
complicated become more and more and
more messy the tension between them gets
more and more unbearable the
externalities ejected by the complicated
into the complex become greater and
greater and greater until the
complicated breaks down and it is my
belief that we're at the stage now where
our complicated institutions are going
to start breaking down left right and
center and so my hope for none of the
above is that we can make a choice
Charles Eisenstein talks about a terrain
of peaks and valleys of understanding
and at our current civilization has led
us to the top of the existing Peak ride
words as has taken us as high as it can
but in order to ascend a higher peak we
first need to descend this one and go
down into the valley down into the
unknown now that can happen in one of
two ways
either we can wait for all of our
systems to collapse around our ears and
send a spiraling into chaos or we can
vote none of the above push this out of
the way clear the table so that we can
start having a proper conversation about
systems that can be created that can
interface effectively with the complex
and by choosing to vote none of the
above we can make that decision to
descend into the valley consciously
deliberately together with a goal in
mind rather than collapsing into it okay
that's I think basically all I want to
say for this video thank you very much
for listening the power of the people's
vote and I think the people should use
it to vote for
[Applause]
you